[Music]
hey hey welcome back
it's day three uh i'm here with my
campers again i'll go and let them
introduce themselves again hi
i'm lila hi i'm bowen
hi i'm i'm mckinley hi i'm keegan
all right we've got all our campers here
today uh what we're going to be doing
today
is um making a game about fish if you
choose a fish theme
uh but before we hop in let's just kind
of quickly glance at some things we
learned last time so
one of the big things we learned last
time is that we learned how to draw
right so we learned about these drawing
tools we're going to continue our
drawing tools some this time
last time it was for the background and
so this time we're going to draw a
sprite together
which should be fun we're also going to
learn like a new way of movement
so before we did avery walking where she
followed the mouse pointer around
that was how she moved uh the hedgehog
moved with this up down left right
keys and then this time we're going to
move in a different way that i call
a race car movement we're also going to
learn about something at the very end
called broadcasting events so we'll get
into that let's look at a solution
for what we're trying to build today so
mine is called fish lunch
so this version was made by bob um and
the idea of this game is that you're the
fish
so i'm nemo here and nemo's trying to
eat his food
so there he just kind of made it to some
food and you're trying not to let these
these things hit you one feature that
you kind of see is i sped up nemo there
so nemo actually got a little faster
so i can use the up and down arrow keys
and then i hit some trash and so i got a
score of three that time
but you can see that there's a lot going
on because we have to worry about our
hero
that's nemo we have to be able to speed
up nemo
and then we also have to be able to slow
down nemo nemo can swim backwards as
well
we've got the food that we're going to
draw um
and then we've got all these enemies
that are around us as well
so don't be surprised if uh today takes
a little longer
that's designed by the camp the first
day kind of an intro the second one it's
a little harder
the third is the hardest day in general
and then we start tapering down summer
at the end so don't be surprised
if you need a couple breaks in this
video but let's go ahead and dive right
in
and go and get started so go ahead and
visit scratch.mit.edu
click on create and it will bring you to
a new project
now what i'm going to do is i'm going to
make my theme
similar to what this one was so fish
themed if you want to use a different
theme
you can but what i'm going to do is i'm
going to choose choose a sprite
and for me i'm going to choose a fish so
here's my fish right here
this fish is kind of interesting because
he's got different costumes
so now i can delete my cat so this fish
has different costumes and sometimes
costumes are like animations
but you can see that this one has
different costumes or just completely
different fish
so i'm gonna pick the fish that i want i
really like the one that looks like nemo
i think he's fun so now i've got my fish
on here
i can change things like his size like
maybe i want him to be a little smaller
so i can have him be teeny tiny you can
pick whatever size fish you want maybe
would be good just like before you can
think about
his directions whether he can rotate all
around or only left right or not rotate
this one i do want to rotate all around
all right so now we've picked out our
hero
and our hero is on our screen if you did
a fish great if you did something
different that's fine
let's do some code first thing we want
to add campers where do you think we
need to start
click on the green flag yeah so event
when green flag clicked so this is where
we start a lot of our games
and then eventually we're going to have
a forever loop but before we do the
forever loop
i first want to set his starting
position and his starting direction
so decide where your fish or whatever
your hero is is going to start your game
so i'm going to choose to start in just
a lower left corner but you can do it
wherever you want
once you position them in that location
you can go to motion
and find this go to xy
and again what's nice about this command
is if you've moved the fish to where you
want so here it's negative 168 negative
you can see that that command the
arguments those things in whites
auto update to where he's at which is
kind of nice that's why i put him in
position
first before i add that command and then
i'm going to grab
something that says point in direction
90. this is so that my fish
starts going this way when the game
begins
now we're ready for our forever loop so
very common in code
to do something forever forever loops
are in control
and here's my forever loop that i'm
going to put on my fish
so a lot of these concepts are things
we've seen before we try to do this by
design and games where we have these
same concepts
over and over and you can kind of see
that there's a little bit of setup stuff
at the start
and then a loop that goes forever now
what i want to do forever
is my fish is always swimming so i'm
going to grab
a move and put it in here
right now it's move 10 steps that's
going to be a little too fast i'm going
to start him at 3
so move 3 steps
if i did run the game right now uh he
would start swimming in a straight line
which would be great um if i stopped the
game and i started again he would swim
in a straight line again
uh straight lines aren't much fun uh we
want to do something
different so i want the left arrow key
and the right arrow key
to let me change my direction so
we want if statements so go to control
and drag over two if statements so one
and then another
and what these if statements want to do
is they want to say
if somebody is pressing the left arrow
key
then we want to rotate left a little bit
then the other one's going to say if
somebody's pressing the right arrow key
we want to rotate right a little bit
so we'll do now we can do one together
then let's do the other
so sensing
if the key space is pressed i don't want
to switch space to be
left arrow so if the key left arrow is
pressed
then inside motion i want to do a left
turn
see if you can do the right turn and
then see if you can try it so right now
my fish can turn to the left
um but he really can't turn uh to the
right yet
so see if you can do that all by
yourself
all right so i added mine uh so now i
can go left
uh or i can go right and he can swim
around
now just for fun the speed right now is
always
three and you'll notice that we don't
need the up
uh or down arrows for this style of
motion so we're going to add a fun
feature
and learn a little bit about variables
so instead of the speed always being
three
let's make a variable so click on
variables
click on make a variable and we're going
to make a variable called
speed that's for this sprite only
so see how there's kind of two options
it can be for all sprites they all share
the variable
or the speed is for the sprite only so
speed
for this sprite only and hit okay now
whenever we make a variable there's
usually three things we need to do
we need to set its value initially so
i'm going to
drag a set uh into my like starting area
so notice how it's near the top and i'm
going to set the
speed to be three so we
we made the variable uh we set its
initial value
um and then we're going to use the
variable so i'm going to go ahead and
take
speed and drop it into move speed steps
so with that change it's the exact same
as it was before
no no no change at all yet right
but usually what we want to do with
variables is we want to create them
we want to initialize their value we
want to use them we also want to change
them
so let's go ahead and do this to change
it let's add two more if statements
i add an if statement for up arrow
and for down arrow so i'll go ahead and
do one of them with you
so if touching up arrow
well with up arrow we want the speed to
go up so i'm going to go to variables
and this time i'm going to say change
the variable so
change speed and i'm going to make it go
up by just a half
so i'm going to go up a half so this
will be kind of hard for you
but we've got the key up arrow makes it
go up by a half
how could down arrow make it go like
down by a half
so you're going to need a negative in
there see if you can do it all by
yourself
all right so i got mine added so i said
if down
arrow pressed then change speed by
negative 0.5
now let's review the code a little bit
before we move on because there's a lot
of little pieces here
so when green flag collect the two
motions i think we got that
here's what all we did was speed we set
it up to the top make sure it says speed
in your code not my variable
by the way sometimes i like to delete
that old nasty my variable
because it just causes me problems right
make sure it says speed speed
speed speed no my variables anywhere so
we set it
we use it and we modify it i think
mine's ready to go so now my fish
can swim around now my fish kind of
turns a little quick
if i wanted to i could change that but
i'm not worried about it the thing i
want to test here is
does my up arrow change my speed oh it
sure does so now i'm kind of zipping and
zooming
um i could also uh slow down so
uh it's interesting i can actually make
my fish to where he stops
which is kind of cool and then this is
not really realistic
but your fish can in fact swim backwards
right
that's fine right but it's a really good
example of variables
all right so let's go ahead and save our
game
i'm going to call mine fish lunch
um and i think we're ready to add our
next sprite
so the next sprite that we're going to
add is the uh actually let's put a
background on first i
my fish is swimming around in white
let's go ahead and choose a background
you can choose any background that's
appropriate for what you want
mine's a fish so mine's underwater so
you can see i've got two good
underwater options i'll just pick this
one so now i've got a background
and now what i really want to do is i
want to go see what my campers have
picked for their
uh because i'm sure that they did not
all pick fish right because they're all
crazy
uh what they picked for their fish what
they picked for the background
and things like that all right neela
what do you make what do you have going
on the party
where the care bears are trying to get
the units
so she made a party with a unicorn uh
and she's got a plan to have like
care bears in there bowen what did you
do i made a draco
a draco that's a type of gecko
make him fly around some yeah i'll make
it that's cool
so my campers uh have a few skills that
we're going to teach you today about how
to get things off the internet so draco
actually came from the internet we'll
teach you how to do that today
uh mckinley's got a dolphin swimming
around so she's also got an underwater
she's zipping and zooming
and then keegan what have you got today
minion uh he's got a minion so yeah so
he also
uh grabbed something from the internet
uh which we will show you uh today
all right so the next thing we want to
do is uh make a new sprite
this next sprite is going to be our food
so you can see that we've got the
the food over here the food what i want
you to do is i want you to practice
drawing
for a sprite so click on um or hover
over
sorry where it says choose a sprite and
in the past we've always just clicked it
right
well clicking it is actually the same as
choose a sprite right so it's the same
thing
but you can also paint a sprite or you
can upload an image of a sprite
this time what i want you to do for your
food is i want you to paint a sprite
so go ahead and click on paint
that will bring up the drawing canvas um
and what i want you to do is i want you
to draw
your food so for example uh my fish food
is just gonna be a few brown circles so
i'm gonna learn about the circle tool
so i set my color to a brown i can
decide if it has an outline or not
maybe i want a thin outline so maybe
i'll make like a really thin outline
um and i'll just draw a couple uh food
pellets right
so this is just kind of fish food you
can also do things with
with different colors if you want so i
can make some of them brown
or maybe i can make another one like a
darker green
[Music]
you can really just kind of draw
whatever you want there's there's no
right or wrong answer
uh to fish food right so feel free to
just play around a little bit
until you're happy with uh with your
food
don't worry about the size when you're
drawing because the size you'll take
care of
with the size that's over here so draw
it big
and then resize it over there so
go nuts until you're really happy with
your food sprites
all right so my camper's got their food
drawn some some some good food out there
let's go into the code for the food so
this is a sprite
so it's got code like most codes it's
going to start off with a win
green flag clicked it's a very common
thing to do
and then the next thing i like to do is
i like to set the starting position of
the food
but it's going to be a little different
i want it to be different every time
so i'm actually going to say go to
random position so you can try this a
couple times
when i hit the game start you can see
one time it showed up up here
and then i hit game start again it
showed up way way down there
and every time you play your game the
food will start
somewhere different which is kind of the
goal
by the way if this fish speed is in your
way you can
you can move it to somewhere different
if you want so like maybe like jam it
way up over here
you could also change its readout so you
can make it like a
number readout if you wanted so you
right click on it
or you could change it to a slider
readout
or you could change it to just the
normal readout just letting you know
that you can kind of move those around a
little bit
i'm going to jam mine in the upper right
hand corner
just to kind of get it out of the way
all right so right now
your food shows up in a random spot but
when you eat the food
nothing happens right so i want to fix
that
so i want my food to forever
be sensing for the fish so the food is
going to check to see if the fish
touches it
so i got to do it forever so the first
thing is i go to control
or add a forever loop one mistake people
sometimes make is they add on an if
statement right now
and that would be bad because it would
just check one time and then never never
again
we want to forever check right so i'm
going to say forever
and then i'm going to do if and then i
want to sense if i'm touching the fish
so the if part is going to be in sensing
i'm going to say
touching mouse pointer
now obviously i don't want the mouse
pointer but that's why that white
drop down is on there so i hit the white
drop down
and now you can select the name of your
sprite
so in this case in my case it's the fish
so if i'm touching the fish
what happens so um i like sounds
so i'm probably going to make some kind
of sound i'm going to see what kind of
sounds
this thing has by default it's got it
it's got a pop sound
pop is okay i could use pop but if you
want to make a different sound just
click on this choose a sound down here
and i always like chomp
so now i can play a pop sound or i can
play a chop sound
so now i've got those kind of like in my
library i go back to the codes you can
easily switch to sounds
or you can go back to code and in code
what i want to do is i want to go sound
and i want to put on a play or sorry
start
sound chomp note that there's two
versions
there's start the sound which means just
play it real quick
and keep moving or there's play until
done
in this case i want to just start it
because i want to immediately do
something else
the next thing i want to do is i want to
give them a point so we're going to keep
a score
and so we're going to need a variable
for score so i've got to make another
variable
so go to variables or like old pros at
variables
you'll notice that this sprite has no
so go and click on make a variable
i'm going to call this variable score
now the score variable
is global right so everybody uses score
the fish increments the score
other people see the score the score is
for all sprites so that's global
so i'm going to hit ok so now he's got a
score variable
somewhere we've got to initialize it to
zero
we could do it we could do this on
either place we could do it on the fish
or we could do it on the food
doesn't matter um since i'm currently
looking at the code for the for the
food um i put it on the food so i set
the score to zero to start
so the same pattern so we made it we
initialized a value
the next thing we want to do is we want
to change it
so inside the if statement
put a change score by 1.
and then the last thing we want to do is
we want to move our food
to a different spot so they they score a
point
and then it moves on you so go to motion
and find go to random position
so you can see that it starts at zero it
goes to random position
if the fish touches it i make the sound
i change the score and i go somewhere
new
let's try it so i run my code so now
whenever i get my food
it makes a chomp i score a point
and it goes somewhere new now since
there's no enemies
the game's pretty easy right so i can
just go pretty fast with my fish
and i can just chomp things away wow
now with no enemies you can do this
until you get bored
but eventually you will get tired of
collecting food
because it's a little bit too easy right
i mean it's still fun
but it's but it's a little bit too easy
all right i'm going to see how my
campers are doing
i want to get them caught up uh show us
what you've got so far
so this is nila's so she's got a unicorn
um and then she's got a um
rainbow that she's uh she's collecting
cool so fun fun theme nila
[Music]
let's see what bowen's got oh bowen did
a great job with drawing
uh he drew a little fly um and he's got
his draco lizard that's flying around
why can't i catch you
oh it's close uh and bow and your score
isn't incrementing yet but we'll fix
that easy peasy okay buddy
okay uh let's have [ __ ] let's see what
you've got
so you've got uh a dolphin uh eating uh
a little tuna fish right uh-huh or like
a goldfish
you did a nice job a little like orange
goldfish nice
keegan what's your theme uh you've got a
minion
uh eating a banana that's a pretty
impressively drawn banana i'm
questioning whether you drew it all or
not
uh but it looks uh it looks great cool
super progress you guys all right i
think we are ready for some enemies
because our game is too easy
so i'm going to add one enemy that's
like from the the library
so we've kind of discovered that you can
either just click on the circle or you
can click on this magnifying glass it's
the same button right
and what mine is is my game is a fish
and so i'm going to add a shark now you
can see that there's a couple different
sharks here
this one is like either a hammerhead
shark or regular shark
and then this shark actually has like an
animation i'm going to add
this shark as you can see it switched
over to his code which we have none
no big surprise we're going to start
with the event
when green flag clips
the next thing that i like to do is i
like to set his starting position
and his starting direction um oh by the
way he's a little big so i'm going to
move him to where i want him
i'm going to adjust his size if
necessary
and so i'm going to have my shark always
start from right here
so if i want to always start from right
there i go to motion
and i drag over a go to xy
again as long as you've set him there
those numbers will just be correct
right that's one thing that i love about
scratch the next thing we're going to do
is we're going to decide what direction
that he should point in so he's going to
just continually move in a line
in some direction now if we ran this
game right now
he would be pointing to the right and
eventually he's going to move he's not
moving yet
let's go and make a move so let's go
control
forever and then in motion we're going
to make him move
and then this is a fun trick
inside movement there's a very special
type of movement it says if on edge
bounce this is kind of fun
[Music]
if on edge bounce so right now if you
run him
he's going to point to the right and
he's just going to go back and forth
the whole time which is kind of neat
right
now that's good i'm happy about how
things are going
but i don't want him to always go to the
right i could set a different direction
for him but i want him to go in a random
direction every time
so here's what we're going to do instead
of saying point in direction 90
i'm going to go to operators and i'm
going to pick a random number
so i'm going to drag over this pick
random and i'm going to put it right
here
on point in direction
uh now this seems like a math lesson
opportunity right now it says
one degree to 10 degrees if i want all
the different options
so like not just one but all the
different options so you can start in
any direction
what number do i need to put here
campers this might be a question for
keegan keegan what's all the way around
the circle
108 not 180 different number double that
much
360. 360. neil i got it
way to go neela so now if i run it uh
one time he picked that direction uh and
then another time he picked a different
direction but this gives him a
a little bit of randomness right so
every time you do it
he goes in a different direction all
right next thing i want to do
is if i hit the fish um something should
happen right so like if i hit the fish
um the the game should end right so i
need an if statement
so i'm going to go into control
i'm going to take an if statement here
and what i want to do is i want to sense
whether i'm touching the fish or not so
i'm going to say touching
fish
so if i'm touching the fish i want
something to happen
in this particular case we're going to
make something interesting happen
we're going to broadcast an event that
we've hit the fish
broadcasting events is something new
it's something we've never seen before
but if i hit the fish i'm going to
scream to everybody i hit the fish
um and then everybody can respond to it
that's that way we know
so events are actually well sorry
they're in the events
area and so i want to broadcast this
event so find where it says
broadcast message one and stick that
inside of here and what i want to do
here is i want to say instead of message
one
i want to broadcast a new message
and i'm going to broadcast a message
called hit
so it's kind of crazy i don't do
anything at all inside of here
i just scream to everybody i hit the
fish
and then everybody can respond to it
including me
right so including me i can respond to
this event
all right so what we want to do is we
want to
find a event that says like when i
receive
hit uh and so it's right here when i
and you can see it says uh message one
i'm gonna switch that to hit
so everybody is gonna listen for this
event
and it's really no different than the
green flag event so the green flag is
when they press the green flag
and this is when the event hit occurs so
what do i want to do
when a hit occurs well the first thing i
want to do is i want to stop
my other script right so i want to stop
moving
so that's in control and this is kind of
confusing but it's
it's stop all but notice how this all
has a white arrow so you know you can
change it
i want to stop the other scripts so
the first thing that happens whenever
somebody hits whether it's this fish or
somebody else
we stop the other script so we're no
longer running that script anymore it's
done
now the only thing that happens is my
code here
just for fun what i want to do is i want
to glide
to the bottom so i try this this is
going to be something new for us
find the glide that has the x and the y
now gliding to the bottom uh the y is
like negative
180 i think that's the very bottom
and the x i don't want to move my
current x so wherever i hit the fish at
from that point i want to glide to the
bottom so the x
we actually there's no number we could
type in there instead we want the
variable that's called
x position so basically that means don't
change my x
so from wherever i'm at i want to glide
to the bottom
straight down which is at negative 180
in the y and i want to keep my x
position the same
you can decide how long to do that i'm
going to do it over two seconds
[Music]
so we're going to try our code now we
are broadcasting this hit message
but the only person so far that's
listening is
just the shark so i'm going to go and
hit play
[Music]
by the way my shark is way too fast i'll
fix that
and so you can see that once um once i
hit the shark
he does that fall to the bottom right
now other people should also listen to
this message
right so when i hit him he falls to the
bottom
all right so it's kind of silly for the
enemy to die but the fish to keep right
on swimming so let's have
the fish also respond to this head event
so come over to the fish's code and now
what we want to do with the fish is we
want to do the same thing we're going to
go to events
and he also is going to respond to the
hit event so when i receive hit
i'm going to do some things as well the
first thing i want to do
is i want to stop that other script that
was what was moving me around i want to
stop it
that's in control it's nor the very
bottom
i think this is confusing it's the one
that says stop all we don't want to stop
all not yet at least
but we want to stop other scripts in
this sprite
so i want to stop all the other scripts
so that's this script right here we're
going to stop doing it
and then we're going to make a sound
we're going to say like
game over or something like that now
normally what we do with sounds
is we go into the sound area and we pick
a sound
but you'll notice that there's different
options here too you can you can choose
the sound
just like you could choose uh sprite
images or you could
select a sound from your computer um or
this is the one we're going to do this
time
you could record a sound so we're going
to record a sound
so click on record it should ask you on
your computer
if you want to allow your microphone to
be used you have to say yes to that
and then you're going to click on record
here game over
so i recorded myself saying game over
once uh
you make a sound you can trim uh these
sides
uh such that it kind of like matches
your sound and then you can save it
you can name it if you want that's
optional i'm going to choose to name
mine
game over and then you can go back into
the code
and now you can use this sound just like
any other sound so i'm going to
start sound game over
and i'm going to play it now and see if
it works so whenever i hit my shark
who's still moving too fast
uh where yeah sure it should say game
over
so see if you can record your sound and
get it to say
game over or whatever you'd like
whenever your fish hits an enemy
all right so it says a message uh when
you when you lose the game says your
game over
let's also have it say something uh to
put your score on the screen
so to say something like in a speech
bubble that's in looks
and so we're going to grab the one that
says say hello for two seconds
now i'm going to zoom in a little bit
here so you can see what i'm about to do
now instead of saying hello
i want to say like you know great job
and then your score uh colon
so i want to tell them what their score
is now we did this last time too
if you want to like put two strings
together it's called
join and it's over in operators so i
want to find the one that says join
i'm going to put it in here on what i
typed was a loss there
so now i'm going to type it again great
job
score colon and then in variables
i'm going to drag over the score
so now when you finish the game so that
i got one point
it says great job score one
mine looked pretty good i want to say it
for a little longer i'm going to say it
for
five seconds just so they can kind of
see their score i'm going to go help my
campers type this but before i do
the last thing we're going to add on to
this script is
stop all so when the game is truly over
um it's nice to put a stop all in there
because you can see my green flag is
still like pressed down
that's because i didn't have that stop
all on there so i'm gonna do it one more
time
then i'm gonna help my campers so says
great job score
zero um and then it actually says um
stop all after five seconds four seconds
is probably
funny i'm gonna go help my campers type
some all right so i got mine tight for
everybody so we're doing pretty good the
only thing i want to change is i want to
change the speed of the enemy
and i also want to change the number of
enemies let's go play with his speed
now what i want to do is i want the game
to get progressively harder
so i'm going to go into my enemy over
here and i'm going to make a variable
and i'm going to call it
enemy speed so enemy speed is going to
be shared by all the enemies there's
eventually going to be a few different
enemies
so it's going to be for all sprites
so we created it like we normally do
we're going to set its value
we could set its value over in the fish
we could set it in the food
doesn't matter i'm going to set it right
here on my enemy code and i'm going to
set it to 10 to start with
and then i'm going to use enemy speed
where it says
move 10
and so now my speed is going to be
variable
i'm going to take my enemy speed and i'm
going to kind of put it up over here
by the other speed just to kind of like
smoosh them together
and so this speed can get increased
other places in the code so what i'm
going to do is i'm going to increase the
speed
other places in the code i'm going to
increase it over where food is at
so this is a neat interaction of things
so if i go over to food
food has totally different code food
increases the score
he's also going to change the enemy
speed so grab a change
enemy speed and put it right in here
and he's gonna bump up the enemy speed
by two
now i know it looks like the speed's
already too fast we're making it faster
that's coming
bear with me but it's kind of the same
pattern we did before we created the
variable
we initialized the variable we modified
it in a different sprite
that's fine and then we used it in this
sprite now what i'm going to do to slow
it down is i'm actually going to go to
control
and i'm going to add a weight of
0.1 seconds
and the reason i'm adding this delay is
that my sprite
has costumes that he can go through so
he can kind of like go through this
animation
so what i'm going to do for my sprite
since she has
different costumes is i'm going to drag
over a next costume
if your sprite only has one costume or
the different costumes don't look like
an animation you don't have to do that
but what i'm going to do here is now
it's going to kind of slow my guy down a
little bit to start with
and he's using his animation now what i
want to do is i want to see if he speeds
up so my fish is going to grab some food
pellets
and so you'll notice that now the enemy
speed for me is at 14
uh 16. so he it slowly
gets faster and faster right
and so you can kind of sense that he's
going faster now and then he ate my fish
head on so i'm actually pretty happy
with my code i've got an enemy speed
that increases
the only thing that i want to do is i
want to have more
enemies right now i could go into the
sprite library and i could get more
enemies
but i'm going to show you another trick
i'm going to show you this
upload sprite so what i'm going to do is
i'm going to go to the internet
so i'm going to go to to google
um and i'm gonna search for some type of
enemy
well if i'm a fish in the ocean one of
my main enemies uh is trash right
so i'm gonna click uh search for um soda
plastic rings so i'm
looking for images so whenever you're
looking for images in google you click
on images
and i actually want a certain type of
images i want images with transparent
backgrounds
you can improve the search results by
clicking on tools
uh color transparent so you type in what
you're searching for
and then you go to images i don't want
just any any images i want to go to
tools
i want transparent background images and
so now i've got some things that i think
that i want so i think that this one
looks pretty good
if it shows you this checker pattern
it's probably a transparent background
so you can right click on it and you can
say save image as
i will warn you that sometimes they
put they cheat like the internet's uh
ornery right
they put a checkerboard background on
there that's not actually transparent
now what i want to do over in sprite is
i want to say upload a sprite
and i'm going to pick my rings
um and so now my rings are part of this
and notice that since they had a
transparent background they look really
good right
i'm going to change their size and then
the nice thing about their code is that
their code is almost identical to the
sharks
the only thing that's different is where
it starts at right
when you have the same code it's nice
and easy you just
drag it from the shark over
and i want to drag both of these things
over
so now you can see my rings as soon as i
zoom out some
they should have the exact same code
where's the codec
all right i guess i'm going to do it
again so drag this one and drop it
on the rings there it came over
and the only thing that's different is
the starting position
so what i like to do is i like to put it
in the position that i want it
go to motion and then i can see that
what i really want is i want this go to
xy
now i can do i can do a couple of
different things i can just drop it in
after this one that would actually work
fine or i can get
rid of that one um or i could have just
changed the numbers in that one
so go add a couple of enemies what would
another good in may be
what did i use in my my first example oh
i used a water bottle
so i'm going to say water bottle
now one thing that annoys me about
google is it lost my my
tools color transparent so i have to
like put that back on every time
i'm not quite sure um and so you have to
try to find a good
um transparent background those are all
pretty good water bottles
i'm just gonna accept this one it'll be
fine right click save images
and i'm going to change there's a
shorter file name so bottle
is a good short name and you can see
i've already done this once
and then i'm going to come over to
scratch again i'm going to say upload
sprite
i'm going to pick that bottle image and
if it's got a good transparent
background
it should show up and kind of integrate
nicely with my game pretty common to
come in huge
i'm just going to make it a smaller size
so i think you kind of see the pattern
um and then you copy your code over from
another one
so you drop it in there you drop it in
there
and then the only thing that's different
about the code this time
is the starting position so go to
xy i'm going to put that one on and take
that one
out so i think that i've got a finished
game
so let's let me go ahead and try it so i
can get the the
the food i'm going to make a full screen
here i can get the food
um and my enemies get just a little bit
harder um and i can speed my fish up if
he's going too slow
uh so i'm going to go and try to get the
food up there oh i'm in trouble
so i got two that time but i think my
game is
done uh which is cool and you can see
uh how your game plays ah just won that
time
um but it should hopefully be uh pretty
fun so i think what i'm gonna do
is i'm gonna help my campers uh get
theirs finished uh
and then i'm going to see how they've
done i also like to click on share by
the way
it gives me a public page i like to send
this link to the grandparents and things
like that
all right campers let's see how you did
all right so you're first so tell us
what you've got
okay
so who's your uh who's your hero here
going around so you've got a unicorn and
care bears huh
[Music]
nina that's so cool did you decide to do
those care bears
i did all three of them all three of
them gotcha that's great
and so you can see that uh neila has a
lot of fun
uh making her game specific to her so
unicorns and care bears
uh bowen what's the uh what's the theme
on your game buddy
i'm a draco a draco all right play it
let's see
so it's a draco gekko um and he's trying
to catch the fly down there
great job so you got to score one and
then what are they scored so fourth
two your score so far is two with it
your best ever yes all right so you've
got the enemies coming towards you so go
catch the fly again
great job buddy nice work all right
we'll show sissy's next
so mckinley let's uh let's see what
you've got so you've got the dolphin
going around he's the hero and the
dolphin is catching the
the goldfish and then she's got three
enemies so she's got a great white shark
an orca so a killer whale cool
so you gotta score a three i love it
[ __ ] really really good
uh and then we got keegan over here
keegan what's your game
keegan is all minions uh so he's got
play again buddy let's see if you can
get get one so he's got a minion
um and then the enemies are these purple
minions so the evil purple minions
uh and his minion is trying to get
bananas
no this is my very last one
great job keegan took a little bit there
all right
so uh a harder game uh so this is
probably going to be our hardest game in
the camp
but i mean if you can get this uh this
working i'd be
really impressed with your efforts uh
things we run this time is each sprite
has its own code science and art come
together in this interesting way so lots
of drawing and things like this
variables can tend to be commonplace uh
and useful
and we learned a new movement style and
about broadcast events
a great job accomplishing the video
today
see you next time bye